<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alicehenley.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://alicehenley.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-06T23:23:32+01:00</updated><id>https://alicehenley.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alice’s adventures!</title><subtitle>Find out about all my cycling, hiking and other adventures I've been up to. Some nice snaps and some info on what to (or not to!) do. Check out my parent website to find out more about me and my scientific research work alicehenley.co.uk</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Writing up en France</title><link href="https://alicehenley.github.io/blog/other/writing-retreat/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Writing up en France" /><published>2019-08-08T16:03:18+01:00</published><updated>2019-08-08T16:03:18+01:00</updated><id>https://alicehenley.github.io/blog/other/writing-retreat</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alicehenley.github.io/blog/other/writing-retreat/">&lt;p&gt;Writing up my PhD thesis would never be a fun task for me but to ease off the pain I have relocated to the calm, quiet atmosphere of Limousin, France for 2 months to try and get it done peacefully. I packed up my flat in London and moved myself, my things and my bike up and took a plane to Limoges. I am tremendously thankful to the wonderful Paul and Caroline (masterminds behind &lt;a href=&quot;https://lejardincreatif.net/&quot;&gt;Le Jardin Créatif&lt;/a&gt;) who very kindly agreed to put me up. Coincidentally, it’s the same place &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/adventures/cycle-tour-france/&quot;&gt;I cycled toured to in 2016&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Packing up and pushing the weight limits of my luggage was horrendously stressful but I won’t bore you with that. I arrived on the 1st of July and so as I write this post now I’ve been here a little over a month. Have I finished half of my thesis, you ask? Well, no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writing-retreat/tigga-hay-loft.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;tigga_hay_loft&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t just been lounging around in the sun like tigga the cat. There are two major reasons and many, many minor reasons why things haven’t gone quite to plan so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Major hiccup 1: I'm creating more work&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My most recent work in my PhD has focused on modelling solutes in liquids computationally (you can read more about this &lt;a href=&quot;/research/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). We only recently had my first paper from this project accepted and I’m really quite proud of it since it is some of my most independant work. However, I feel like I’ve only just started and have so much more to try! Initially, I had intended on stopping research in July to focus purely on my thesis but I’m not ready to drop this project and it will be some time before anyone would pick it up again so I’m finishing what I started. I have no regrets about doing this at all. If I was to leave it to dry up and die, it would be like leaving a parenthesis open “(“ but never closing it. Eugh.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am able to continue this work remotely and I’ve already managed to get so much more done out here without the noise and distractions of the office in London. I’m excited about this project and keen to see it through. But yes, this is just adding to what I need to write in my thesis… Sorry, future Alice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writing-retreat/swallowtail-moth.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;swallowtail_moth&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Major hiccup 2: heat waves and being a giraffe&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giraffe’s have extremely high blood pressures to ensure enough blood goes from their heart all the way up to their brain. In that sense, I’m not like a giraffe at all. 
I’m fairly tall though (178 cm), have quite low blood pressure, cycling muscles in my legs but the arms of a t-rex. So I get bad head rushes and faint sometimes. In the “50 shades of grey” climate we have in UK, this is managable but this summer Europe has been hit with record high temperatures and out here in Limousin we’ve had several days of &amp;gt;40°C in the shade. For reference, internal body temperature is around 37°C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My precious British skin can’t deal with it! So I’ve had many days where I can’t do much at all, delaying the write up even more so. This got me really quite down, to be honest. Can’t work, can’t bike ride, can’t do anything :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the weather has cooled off a bit since and I’ve felt a lot better - I’ve never been so happy to see rain!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The minor factors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may have harped on about how I have fewer distractions over here, but it’s not fair to say there are none at all…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writing-retreat/white-cat-garden.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;white_cat_garden&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there’s the 4 cats that get lots of fuss from me. Then there’s the sourdough bread I’ve been working on, the tortilla press I’ve built and with it a recipe to tweak. There’s helping about with Paul and Caroline’s businesses wherever I can. I’ve been taking photos of nature and camping in the garden &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/adventures/nightsky-photography1/&quot;&gt;attempting astrophotography&lt;/a&gt;. There’s the occassional bike ride when it’s not too hot, finding new courgette recipes and this miffed-off owl I made (with lots of help from Paul!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writing-retreat/angy-owl.png&quot; alt=&quot;angry_owl&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I’ve been making decent headway into my calculations. I’ve done some work on it almost every day and I’m still making more progress than I would in London. C’est la vie!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Sorry about that. “)” There we go. Much better. &lt;a href=&quot;https://xkcd.com/859/&quot;&gt;Relevant xkcd&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="france" /><category term="photography" /><category term="nightsky" /><summary type="html">Writing up my PhD thesis would never be a fun task for me but to ease off the pain I have relocated to the calm, quiet atmosphere of Limousin, France for 2 months to try and get it done peacefully. I packed up my flat in London and moved myself, my things and my bike up and took a plane to Limoges. I am tremendously thankful to the wonderful Paul and Caroline (masterminds behind Le Jardin Créatif) who very kindly agreed to put me up. Coincidentally, it’s the same place I cycled toured to in 2016.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alicehenley.github.io/images/writing-retreat.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Night sky photography: take 1</title><link href="https://alicehenley.github.io/blog/adventures/nightsky-photography-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Night sky photography: take 1" /><published>2019-08-04T16:03:18+01:00</published><updated>2019-08-04T16:03:18+01:00</updated><id>https://alicehenley.github.io/blog/adventures/nightsky-photography-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alicehenley.github.io/blog/adventures/nightsky-photography-1/">&lt;p&gt;Besides the odd attempt to snap the moon, I’ve not really tried photographing the night sky. However, I am a sucker for those photos with star trails in the distance and a lit up tent in the foreground. Hence, I must learn!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I camped out in the field here in La Guinandie (with no rain fly - ooh what a novelty!) and tried taking some photos of the sky at different points in the night. I use a Nikon D3200 DSLR. Here’s my first attempt:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Night one&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/night-sky-photography-1/grainy-AF.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;grainy_AF&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;ISO 12800, 70 mm, f/9.0, 5.2 sec.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably grainy, no thanks to that ISO. I was also too lazy to switch out my telemacro lens back to kit lens. Nether-the-less, not terrible. I had also learnt how difficult it is to focus on the stars and did so by trial and error which was terribly time-consuming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to sleep and left the camera running a long exposure to try and capture some long star trails:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/night-sky-photography-1/trails.1.png&quot; alt=&quot;trails1&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;ISO 100, 70 mm, f/4.0, 1802 sec.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again - better than expected but being too lazy to switch lens was a big fault here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Night two&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now using the kit lens! So I can get a focal length of 18mm. I also set up my focus on the moon before it went down over the horizon. This seemed to work well to focus on the stars well but I had to be very careful not to adjust the focus while moving the camera around. I soon learnt that switching on autofocus while moving helped with this but obviously only if I did not open the shutter while autofocus is on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/night-sky-photography-1/moon-in-tree.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;moon_in_tree&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we had visited a vide grenier (car boot sale) that day and I bought a solid, heavy tripod for 2 euros. This has worked tremendously well to stabilise the camera during long exposures when compared to my cheapo Amazon basics tripod.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/night-sky-photography-1/trails-trees-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;trails_trees_2&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;ISO 100, 18 mm, f/3.5, 1357 sec.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pretty happy with this one. Still needs some noise reduction but I can live with this for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Night three&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Night three and I worked a bit on framing a bit better. Sort of. Here are two photos not terribly well-framed but star trails are great :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/night-sky-photography-1/trails-trees-3-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;trails_trees_3_2&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;ISO 400, 18 mm, f/3.5, 773 sec.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/night-sky-photography-1/trails-trees-3-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;trails_trees_3_1&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;ISO 100, 18 mm, f/3.5, 1802 sec.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then trying to get the house into frame, I captured several long exposures and stacked them to create the following. I don’t have a timed shutter release and so the exposures each had different shutter speeds making stacking a bit tedious but the end result is not bad. Still not perfect and there’s things to improve on - I’m definitely hooked!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/night-sky-photography-1/trails-over-house-short.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;tails_over_house_gd&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;ISO 100, 18 mm, f/3.5, 1802 sec&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/trails-over-house.png&quot; alt=&quot;trails_over_house_sum&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;ISO 100, 18 mm, f/3.5, approx. 2 hours total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="france" /><category term="photography" /><category term="nightsky" /><summary type="html">Besides the odd attempt to snap the moon, I’ve not really tried photographing the night sky. However, I am a sucker for those photos with star trails in the distance and a lit up tent in the foreground. Hence, I must learn!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alicehenley.github.io/images/trails-over-house.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cycling in France from St Malo, Bretagne - Vayres, Limousin: j’adore le vélo en France!</title><link href="https://alicehenley.github.io/blog/adventures/cycle-tour-france/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cycling in France from St Malo, Bretagne - Vayres, Limousin: j'adore le vélo en France!" /><published>2016-08-30T16:53:18+01:00</published><updated>2016-08-30T16:53:18+01:00</updated><id>https://alicehenley.github.io/blog/adventures/cycle-tour-france</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alicehenley.github.io/blog/adventures/cycle-tour-france/">&lt;p&gt;While solo cycle touring from St Malo to Limousin via the west coast of France I met wonderful people, enjoyed the simplicity of cycling in france and learnt a lot about travelling alone abroad. Of course, also the importance of sun cream, well-fitting bike shorts and a decent tent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following map shows highlights the route I took and the points I stopped over night. This journey was a long one, with 8 days of cycling, yet I only cover a tiny fraction of the vast area of France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/total-map.png&quot; alt=&quot;total-map&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Contents&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-plan&quot;&gt;The plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#kit-list&quot;&gt;Kit list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#day1&quot;&gt;Day 1, départ: Saint Malo - Réminiac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#day2&quot;&gt;Day 2, rest day&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#day3&quot;&gt;Day 3: Réminiac - Missilac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#day4&quot;&gt;Day 4: Missilac - Saint-Nazaire bridge - La Bernerie-en-Retz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#day5&quot;&gt;Day 5: La Bernerie-en-Retz - Île de Noirmoutier - Saint-Hilaire-de-Riez&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#day6&quot;&gt;Day 6: Saint-Hilaire-de-Riez - L’Aiguillon Sur Mer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#day7&quot;&gt;Day 7: L’Aiguillon Sur Mer - Mauzé-Sur-Le-Mignon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#day8&quot;&gt;Day 8: Mauzé-Sur-Le-Mignon - Nanteuil-en-Vallée&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#day9&quot;&gt;Day 9, the final stretch: Nanteuil-en-Vallée - La Guinandie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#reflection&quot;&gt;On reflection…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;the-plan&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The plan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have friends that live in Vayres, Limousin - not far from Rochechouart/Limoges - and having done a little bit of cycling around there and other parts of France on family holidays here and there, I knew how fantastic it is cycling in France. The roads are perfect, other road users respect cyclists and the atmosphere of cycling through a village in rural France is second to none! And so it wasn’t long before I had conjured up the idea to cycle from the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;like cycling?   &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-check&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;like camping?   &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-check&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;want a chellenge?   &lt;i class=&quot;fas fa-check&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was living in Bournemouth at the time and so it was easy peasy to nip on a ferry from Poole over to France at various points along the north coast of Bretagne (Brittany). This only cost about £50 and provided plenty of opportunity to meet others cycling in France - look at all the bikes in the photo below. We also stopped off at Jersey so I experienced the novelty of Jersey £1 notes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/packing_bikes-on-ferry.png&quot; alt=&quot;packing_ferry&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of route planning, I largely kept to eurovélo route 1 along the atlantic coast of France with a few voie vertes (green ways/bridle paths) here and there before turning in land for Limousin along country roads. I bought a tonne of maps that I didn’t really use as it was all well-signposted and my phone had enough battery throughout for times I was unsure. I gave myself plenty of time to make the trip with a few days off should I want them so I was relaxed on daily milage. I marked out possible campsites near the route on the maps and bookmarked them on my maps.me app (10/10 would recommend).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;kit-list&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Kit list&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the photo above, you can see my packing ‘method’ with everything I took in frame. I had two rear panniers, a stuffsack on top of the panniers and a handlebar bag to pack it all in. Generally speaking, I carried camping/cooking equipment, clothes, basic bike repair tools, basic first aid and toiletries, (too much) food as well as important documents etc. But to summarise the important bits of gear for the enthusiasts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bike: Dawes Galaxy Plus 2014&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Panniers: Ortlieb Back Roller City Panniers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bar bag: Edinburgh revolution bar bag 3L&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tent: Berghaus Peak Solo 3.1&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleeing mat: Thermarest Trail Lite (Womens)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleeping bag: Robens Caucasus 600 Sleeping Bag 2014&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stove: homemade can stove (runs on meths)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;day1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Day 1, départ: Saint Malo - Réminiac&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stopped the night before in an airbnb in St Malo not too far from the port which worked nicely and gave me a fresh start for the first proper day in the saddle. Sadly the day began with dual carriageways before crossing over the D168 bridge towards Dinan and getting off the busy roads and on to the Bretagne voie verte 3 which is a beautiful path that runs from St Malo to Rhuys. I was so happy to be off the busy roads, I took a selfie! Very unlike me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/first-voie-verte.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first day I continued to cycle along the Bretagne voie verte 3 to a village near Ploermel called Réminiac, where my grandparents have a little house. This was a long day of cycling &amp;gt;100 miles with all my gear but quite flat so can’t complain. However, I did find the bib shorts I wore to not be the best fit for the saddle and struggled a little in that department…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;day2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Day 2, rest day&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the poor choice of shorts for my long day of cycling on day 1, I took day 2 off to relax in Réminiac. Although this did include a 40 km ride to a supermarket in order to replace my Grandpa’s beer I drank the night before by comical volumes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/gpas-beer.png&quot; alt=&quot;gpas_beer&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;day3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Day 3: Réminiac - Missilac&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day was a good 75 km in the saddle further south to just over the Bretagne border in Missilac. More dusty, flat canals!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_2_photos&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now (just!) into the Pays de la Loire region, I had my first night of camping at the municipal site in Missilac - perfectly fine and quiet site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-2-camping.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_2_camp&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The generously-sized emplacements at a lot of the municipal sites made my humble little setup look really quite small. Nice to have lots of space to dry my cycling shorts though! My homemade meths stove worked beautifully throughout the trip but I took plenty of care not to light the dry grass. At the end of each day, post shower/tea, I would look over my map for the following day. Comparing possible routes, plotting possible camp sites etc. This night I made the decision to leave the eurovelo 1 (EV1) which would continue in land towards Nantes and return back to the coast along la Loire. La Loire is famously fabulous to cycle along but I was a bit bored of cycling along rivers/canals and had little desire to visit Nantes. This meant crossing the Saint-Nazaire bridge - a task I wouldn’t recommend to inexperienced cyclists, and something my Grandpa insisted I should not do (sorry Grandpa!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;day4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Day 4: Missilac - Saint-Nazaire bridge - La Bernerie-en-Retz &lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cycle from Missilac to the St Nazaire bridge was fantastic. Flat cycle path with road markings and signposts that were scaled down from normal road size - a cute touch! You can just about see the bridge in the distance looking quite ominous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-3-st-nazaire-approach.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_3_st-naz-approach&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Saint-Nazaire bridge runs along a busy dual carriageway but narrows at the bridge where cyclists may join (cycling is forbidden either side of the bridge on the D road). The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint-Nazaire_Bridge&quot;&gt;wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; tells me the bridge spans over the mouth of la Loire for a rather intimidating 3356 m. Such a distance wouldn’t be a problem usually but with touring gear and the proximity of the cars, the long slog uphill took longer than I care to admit. Here are some pics I just about managed while cycling (excuse quality!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-3-st-nazaire.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_3_st-naz-bridge&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the bike lane I’m currently in, the cars in a national speed limit zone and the rather intimidating length of bridge in the distance. &lt;strong&gt;I was grinning ear to ear.&lt;/strong&gt; I was doing maybe 7 kmph uphill, taking in some great views and having so much fun! Definitely a highlight of my trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-3-lunch.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_3_lunch&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side, I had a spot of lunch and continued down the EV1 along the coast to a campsite I can’t honestly recommend, Camping La Goélette in La Bernerie-en-Retz. Facilities were awful, owners were not very nice and it was more expensive than it should have been. However, it’s location is fantastic - right on the ocean front. I met a dutch family later on who had also stayed here and they agreed in how crap this site was. Which, I must say, made me feel a lot better!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make matters worse, my tent pole snapped while I was putting it up, getting me down a bit. But everything can be solved with duct tape, of course! And this held for the rest of the trip - phew.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;day5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Day 5: La Bernerie-en-Retz - Île de Noirmoutier - Saint-Hilaire-de-Riez &lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EV1 brought another new experience for me as I continued south into the Vendée. A tidal island!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mapouter&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;gmap_canvas&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; id=&quot;gmap_canvas&quot; src=&quot;https://maps.google.com/maps?q=passage%20du%20gois&amp;amp;t=&amp;amp;z=13&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;iwloc=&amp;amp;output=embed&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.embedgooglemap.net/blog/20-off-discount-for-elegant-themes-divi-sale-coupon-code-2019/&quot;&gt;elegantthemes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;style&gt;.mapouter{position:relative;text-align:right;height:500px;width:600px;}.gmap_canvas {overflow:hidden;background:none!important;height:500px;width:600px;}&lt;/style&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Passage du Gois connects the mainland to Île de Noirmoutier, a beautiful island full of oak forests. The passage is a paved-over sandbank about 4.5 km long that floods twice daily. I met the passage by surprise, and didn’t check the tide times in advance so had to wait around a while for the water levels to lower. However, it made a good opportunity to catch up with the other touring cyclists I had met en route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-4-tidal-passage.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_4_tidal-passage&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See how far down the water is, and how much traffic I was stuck behind - huff! Cycling around the island was short but sweet before heading back over a bridge to the mainland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-4-ile.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_4_ile&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to some more long, flat pretty scenery to cycle through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-4-vendee1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_4_vendee&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-4-vendee2.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_4_vendee2&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then finishing up in a municipal site in Saint Hilaire-de-Riez for the night before a good day of riding the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;day6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Day 6: Saint-Hilaire-de-Riez - L'Aiguillon Sur Mer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I woke up early, packed up and had my brekky by the sea. The area north of La Rochelle is quite busy/touristy in August and so it’s nice to set off early to get some kilometres in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-5-brekky.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_5_brekky&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cycling through some of the more touristy towns was interesting and the cycling paths there were absolutely perfect. Winding flat asphalt along the coastline. Brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-5-paths.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_5_paths&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managed a very enjoyable 90 km on these paths that day. Along the way I even saw an otter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-5-otter.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_5_otter&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished the day off at another municipal site, Camping De La Baie L’Aiguillon Sur Mer. I cannot recommend the site enough for those bike touring the coast. They have a special “accueil vélo” (bikes welcome) with a dedicated area for cyclists which was a sizable field with a wood shelter, tables, benches, a clothes rack, sockets to charge your phone and overall quite cheap. Only downside is that I accidentally flashed some people having not closed the shower door properly - oops!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started to see signs for La Rochelle which indicated that I would soon be leaving the coast and the EV1 to move inland towards Limousin on my own route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;day7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Day 7: L'Aiguillon Sur Mer - Mauzé-Sur-Le-Mignon&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 70 km and an unwelcome headwind took me from L’Aiguillon Sur Mer to Mauzé-Sur-Le-Mignon, crossing into La Charente Maritime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-6-paths.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_6_paths&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this point, I had realised my maps were pretty much dead weight. I only had a couple of days left and plenty of phone battery for directions so I utilised my bar bag with a little mascot I called Vinnie the véloceraptor. It’s amazing what keeps you entertained when cycling all day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-6-vinnie.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_6_vinnie&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found navigating between the rural villages really easy and the scenery just as wonderful (if not a little more varied/interesting) than that of the EV1. It was fantastic rolling through these little villages and having the locals cheer you on, such a wonderful spirit to cycling in France. &lt;strong&gt;J’adore le vélo en France.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;day8&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Day 8: Mauzé-Sur-Le-Mignon - Nanteuil-en-Vallée&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now fully off the winding paths of the EV1 and on proper tarmac roads, I could make decent headway in land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-7-route.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_7_route&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;90 km took me to the municipal site at Nanteuil-en-Vallée (Camping Municipal Le Val De L’Argentor) which is another wonderful site I can strongly recommend for backpackers/cyclists. There was almost no one else there, the town was trés joli and the lovely woman running the site let me stay &lt;strong&gt;COMPLETELY FREE!&lt;/strong&gt; Happy days!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all going to plan, I would only have one day left to go before arriving at my final destination, La Guinandie, Limousin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;day9&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Day 9, the final stretch: Nanteuil-en-Vallée - La Guinandie&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My final day in the saddle was relaxed; I was in no rush. I even let my tent fully dry off the dew. The days had been hotter and hotter since I began so it was nice to relax a little. With no worries of losing precious phone battery, I played some music and just had a jolly good day cycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/biketourfrancewindmills.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_8_windmill_cover_shot&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was great entering the national park of Limousin and seeing a change of scenery. More trees, more farmland and a more undulating landscape. I was particularly excited when I spotted some Limousin cows!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-8-moos-villages.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_8_moos_villes&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this point I was really excited to finish my journey and have a decent conversation with someone (my French only goes so far!) But I managed to force myself to stop for lunch in some scarce shade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-8-cornfield.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_8_cornfield&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last few kms were perhaps the toughest going physically as there was a lot of height to gain and the heat was immense. However, mentally not-so-challenging as my goal was in sight! After one more big push up a long hill, I had reached Vayres, the village closest to La Guinandie. I had ran out of water (3 bottles yikes!) but I was elated, just an easy pedal to La Guinandie!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/cycling-day-8-fin.png&quot; alt=&quot;cyc_day_8_fin&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is me at my final destination in La Guinandie (I’m not the most photogenic!) After a few glasses of water I was back down on Earth ready for a catch up and shower. Here I am a few days later with a little kitten on my lap - the most perfect way to end an adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cycling-tour-france/fin-kitty.png&quot; alt=&quot;fin_kitty&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;reflection&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;On reflection...&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This journey was a fantastic adventure that was better than I even imagined. The planning was relaxed, the weather was kind and the cycling was amazing. I have wrote this blog post in Aug 2019, exactly 3 years following and it remains my biggest adventure to date. However, having recapped I feel that may be soon to change!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend anyone interested in cycle touring to give it a go. The eurovelo routes never get very hilly and are easy to navigate. I would pass so many families touring with all their bikes in a line like ducklings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Some note-worthy things I learned:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take it easy, try and take in more culture&lt;/strong&gt; - sometimes when travelling alone it’s easy to get caught up with just moving forward and you forget there’s always time to stop and smell the flowers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wear well-fitting bib shorts&lt;/strong&gt; - this speaks for itself.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suncream any exposed skin&lt;/strong&gt; - this includes that gap between your shorts and top on your back. Ouch.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t be afraid to go against what Grandpa said&lt;/strong&gt; - crossing the St Nazaire bridge was exhilarating and remains one of the most memorable moments of the trip.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy a decent tent&lt;/strong&gt; - and always carry duct tape! This could have been disasterous.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Camping municipal sites are your friend&lt;/strong&gt; - they’re regulated, great for tourers, usually have a shop nearby and I never had a problem with them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Close the door when you shower&lt;/strong&gt; - I apologise to the family of four that had to see that. And yes, they were tanlines.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t carry too much food&lt;/strong&gt; - when visiting the land of gourmet food, don’t eat cuppa soup for tea every day. Take in some local food (see first point).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please get in touch if you have cycled the route or are intending on doing so, I would love to hear about it/help you out. Get those bikes out the shed, oil ‘em up, pump up the tyres and go for a spin!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I have since sold this bike to the wonderful Cassie who has given it the life it deserves - touring south America for six months &lt;a href=&quot;https://touringtheandes.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;see their blog.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’ll write a post on my experience with this tent and compare to other 1 man tents - coming soon! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="france" /><category term="solo" /><category term="tour" /><category term="cycle" /><category term="bike" /><summary type="html">While solo cycle touring from St Malo to Limousin via the west coast of France I met wonderful people, enjoyed the simplicity of cycling in france and learnt a lot about travelling alone abroad. Of course, also the importance of sun cream, well-fitting bike shorts and a decent tent!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://alicehenley.github.io/images/biketourfrancewindmills.png" /></entry></feed>